"Ultra-Processed Foods:
Concerns, Controversies, and Exceptions"
And now for our final speaker of the conference.
He is the founder of NutritionFacts.org,
which has over 2,000 educational videos
on pretty much any topic on
nutrition that you could want.
And over the last couple of years,
we’ve learned How Not to Die,
How Not to Diet, How Not to Age.
And today, he is answering a burning
question on everyone’s minds.
And that is,
what is the role of ultra-processed
plant-based foods in our diet?
Ladies and gentlemen,
it is an absolute honor to
welcome our final speaker,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Hey, hey, hey! Welcome everyone.
I love this conference so much.
So honored to be here.
Alright.
There is no conference I’d rather
be premiering a new talk for,
so let’s do this.
Modern nutrition science began about a century ago
in the context of nutrient deficiency diseases.
So, there were editorials with
titles like “Sugar as Food,”
heralding sugar as one of the
cheapest sources of calories.
For a mere six cents, you could
buy three thousand calories.
What a bargain!
But the Nutrient Deficiency era
gave way to the Dietary Excess era.
No longer were we dying of nutrient
deficiency diseases, like scurvy,
as much as we were dying from
nutrient excess diseases,
like obesity and heart disease.
So, it became more about
avoiding too many calories,
too much saturated fat,
too much sugar, too much sodium,
but either way still focused on nutrients.
This allowed food companies
to get away with abominations
like frosting-filled cereal,
because it was fortified with
twelve vitamins and minerals,
50% better than the measly eight
in Marshmallow Froot Loops.
However, food, not nutrients, is
the fundamental unit in nutrition.
And to their credit,
the field of nutrition started moving
toward a more holistic view itself.
So, first generation dietary guidelines
emphasized individual nutrients
moved on to second generation
food-based dietary guidelines,
which largely converged on encouraging
diets rich in vegetables, fruits,
legumes—which are beans, split
peas, chickpeas, and lentils—
whole grains and nuts,
but an area of emerging importance
was the degree of food processing.
What if, when it comes to nutrition and health,
it’s not so much the food or the nutrients
as much as the level of processing?
For instance, a food-based dietary
guideline might say something like
“Eat more vegetable soup.” Great!
But there’s vegetable soup, and
then there’s vegetable soup.
Are we talking a
clean-out-the-fridge vegetable soup?
A health-haloed quinoa and kale organic
with a heart-stopping 1,200 milligrams of sodium?
How about a vegetable soup with
more salt than there are vegetables?
Or a vegetable flavor soup that
has more artificial colors and MSG
than it has vegetables.
All soup is not the same.
The degree of processing matters.
Ultra-processed foods are these
industrial formulations which,
besides salt, sugar, oils, and fats,
include substances that are
really not used in cooking,
like added ﬂavors, colors, artificial sweeteners,
emulsiﬁers, and other additives
used to imitate real foods,
like a frosted grape Pop Tart
with more grapes on the front of the package
than are actually in it,
with less grapes than there are salt,
but it may artificially taste like grapes
and look like grapes because of
one, two, three, four, five different food dyes.
Simply put, ultra-processed foods are foods
that can’t be made in a home kitchen,
because they have been chemically
or physically transformed
using industrial processes.
They typically contain little or no whole foods,
are ready-to-consume or heat up,
and are fatty, salty, or sugary
and depleted in dietary fiber and other nutrients.
So, that’s like all the sweet, fatty, salty snacks
like potato chips, ice cream, soda, candy,
French fries, burgers, hot dogs,
chicken nuggets, fish sticks.
Basically, everything in a box or a bag.
Why not just call them “packaged foods”?
Well, they were actually thinking about it,
but they were afraid that some consumers
would look at like a bag of apples
and get confused or something.
But what is so revolutionary
about this concept of ultra-processed foods?
I mean, wasn’t fatty, salty,
sugary junk always a bad idea?
Why isn’t it enough to just tell
people to stay away from junk?
Because, Diet Coke.
Diet soda is the perfect example
of why a new kind of term like
ultra-processed can be so useful.
Because it has no calories.
No fat. No sugar. So, no problem, right?
Well then, why is diet soda consumption
associated with premature death,
stroke, heart disease, hypertension,
diabetes, metabolic syndrome, leukemia?
And most studies controlled for body weight;
so, it’s not just because heavier
people are more likely to drink it.
Health risks are not only related
to the nutritional quality
of ultra-processed foods but also
to the presence of additives.
No apparent calories, fat, sugar, or salt,
but contains caramel color,
which results in the formation
of 4-methylimidazole,
which is a potential human carcinogen.
And contains aspartame,
also recently classified as
possibly cancer-causing in humans
And contains phosphoric acid
which is a phosphate additive
that may be damaging our health as well.
And contains a benzoate preservative.
If you remove artificial colorings
and benzoate preservatives
from the diets of preschoolers
and then randomize them to be slipped a placebo
or a hidden cocktail of colors and benzoate,
there is a significant reduction
in hyperactive behavior
when they removed these compounds
and then a significant increase
in hyperactive behavior
when they got the colorings and benzoate
compared to getting the placebo.
Now, of course, it could have been the colors,
not the benzoate, but that’s one of the problems.
As little as we know about the
effects of these individual additives,
we know even less what
combinations of them can do.
There is a large body of evidence
suggesting toxicity from certain food colors,
preservatives, sweeteners, and emulsifiers,
in part sometimes through our gut microbiome.
Now, industry apologists argue
that the FDA carefully evaluates food additives
to make sure that they are
safe, until they’re not.
In fact, to show the system works,
they cite the removal of six
carcinogenic artificial flavors in 2018.
Artificial flavors that had
been in the food supply,
approved for safety, since 1964.
So, we were exposed for more than
50 years before they were banned.
And that’s their example of the system working!
Aspartame, NutraSweet, was officially recognized
as a potential human carcinogen in 2023,
42 years after the FDA’s
own public board of inquiry
opposed approval based on it
causing brain tumors in animals
in the industry’s own studies.
This included several FDA scientists
who didn’t think it should be approved.
The FDA Commissioner, however,
rejected these concerns and approved it anyway,
before leaving the agency to enjoy
a $1,000 a day consultancy position
with the aspartame company’s PR firm.
And then, the FDA actually prevented
the National Toxicology Program
from doing further cancer testing.
Meanwhile, literally tens of millions of pounds
made its way into the food supply.
Remember when the food industry thought
partially hydrogenated oils was a good idea?
Let’s replace saturated fats with trans fats.
Although many countries now restrict their use,
trans fats continue to kill an
estimated half-million people
around the world every year.
Of course, saturated fat is also probably
killing hundreds of thousands a year,
but the point is that trans fats from
partially hydrogenated vegetable oil
killed people for decades before
there were any limits on it.
The FDA didn’t ban it until 25 years
after the first solid evidence that it
increased the risk of heart disease,
and meanwhile, every single one of those years,
trans fats were killing an
estimated 50,000 Americans a year.
That is quite the death toll
that can be laid at the feet of
the ultra-processed food industry.
But they originally thought it was safe!
That’s the problem.
Any time a chemical company
comes up with a new preservative
or sweetener or artificial color,
we have no idea how it is going
to turn out decades later.
So, we can start to see the value of
this ultra-processed food concept,
in which an entire category of products
is essentially presumed
guilty until proven innocent.
This drives the food industry crazy,
but look at their track record,
look at the trail of bodies they’ve left behind.
If additives are the problem, well then,
why not just stick to so-called clean label foods,
made with simple, recognizable ingredients,
no matter how the food is processed.
But that’s assuming additives
are the only other reason
that ultra-processed foods may be unhealthy.
Harmful additives are just one of many ways
ultra-processed foods have been linked to disease.
At least the food additives
are listed on the label;
so, we could avoid them if we wanted to.
Unlisted are some of the sneakier ways
ultra-processed foods may be unhealthy.
Harmful additives are just one of the ways
that ultra-processed foods
have been linked to disease.
Like advanced glycation end
products (AGEs), for example.
Increasing evidence has shown
that uptake of dietary AGEs,
advanced glycation end products,
is closely related to the
occurrence of many chronic diseases:
diabetes, chronic kidney disease,
osteoporosis, and Alzheimer’s disease.
In fact, it’s hard to find
a single age-related disease
not associated with AGEs.
Dietary AGEs are abundant
in highly processed food,
because thermal treatments are commonly used,
but thermal treatment just means heat;
so, we can get AGEs from industrial processing
or just from home cooking.
So, let’s look at some examples.
Canned corn has 20 units of AGEs per serving,
compared to corn chips at 151
and corn pops cereal at 373.
Rice only has 9, but rice crackers 275,
and Rice Krispies has 600.
So, you might be at the store
and see some a no-salt-added rice crackers
or a no-sugar-added puffed
rice cereal and be like,
“Oh, it’s just straight rice.
Perfect—one ingredient.”
But no, because of the processing,
it’s not just that one ingredient.
A boiled potato has 17 per serving,
potato chips 865, and fast-food fries over 1,500.
So, ultra-processed plant foods can have
nearly 100 times more of these toxins
than minimally-processed plant foods.
But even raw, unprocessed animal foods
start out with high levels
and just go up from there.
Instead of the 10 or 20 in
cooked whole plant foods,
fish, poultry, and meat start out at
around 500 or more in their raw state
and then jump into the thousands once cooked,
which is still considered minimal processing,
though processed or ultra-processed meat
can exceed 10,000 per serving.
Although these contaminants are not
limited to ultra-processed foods,
you can see how just considering foods
based on their listed ingredients
fails to capture how food processing
can sometimes transform food
at a molecular level.
So, it’s clear that just using
this kind of clean label strategy
of sticking to foods with simple
ingredient lists isn’t going to cut it,
since you’re never going to read
something like AGEs on a label.
It’s the processing itself,
whether traditional or industrial,
that is affecting the healthfulness of the food.
In the latest dietary guidance document
from the American Heart Association,
they advise choosing minimally processed foods,
instead of ultra-processed foods.
Now, of course, they’re not
telling people to eat a steak,
which is considered minimally processed,
because they also emphasize
that we should eat foods low in
saturated fat and cholesterol.
But just like there can be unhealthy
unprocessed foods, like steak,
they suggest there may be some
healthy ultra-processed foods,
like what about, plant-based
milk and meat substitutes.
Admonitions against the consumption of products
simply because they are classified
as ultra-processed foods
may impair society’s acceptance
of a plant-based diet—
thus preventing any related health
advantages from being realized.
And indeed, that does appear
to be a significant reason
why many people avoid these products.
Is that a good thing?
Is that a bad thing?
Are plant-based alternatives healthier
than conventional animal products?
Let’s find out.
Food Compass is a nutrient-profiling system
that rates foods on a scale from 1 to 100,
with 1 being least healthy
and 100 being most healthy.
Eight thousand foods have been scored;
so, you can see where your favorite food falls.
And when I have my laptop next to me,
I ask people to yell out their favorite foods,
and we look up to see what the score is,
and they’re all disappointed that their
raspberries are only 93 or something,
but unfortunately, laptop’s in the back.
Here are some examples of perfect 100 foods,
and foods that score the worst,
all the way from kale down to Coca-Cola.
OK, so the main objective of
ultra-processed “fake” foods
is to imitate real foods.
Like strawberry Pop Tarts trying
to mimic real strawberries.
When you start with a perfect-100
food like strawberries,
the only way to go is down.
So, fruit is better than
fruity-shaped marshmallows.
But when the “real” food is ultra-processed meat,
processed meat, or unprocessed meat, or dairy,
there is a lot of room for improvement.
Food Compass has scored nine
ultra-processed meatless alternatives.
Let’s compare them to the closest
conventional meat matches.
In every single case, the
plant-based meat was rated higher,
healthier, and sometimes by a large margin.
Nearly all scored at least twice as high.
Or three times the health score, seven times,
20 times, even 60-fold higher.
Other common nutrient scoring systems
all found the same general trend.
Now, better than chicken would be chickpeas.
And better soybeans than soy burgers—
soybeans are another perfect-100 food,
but the choice on the Burger King
menu is between this and that,
not between this and that.
(Though, of course, there is a third choice:
not ending up at Burger King.)
This was just a few products
though, just as an illustration.
A 2024 systematic review identified nine studies
using nutritional scoring for the
assessment of over 2,000 meat alternatives
and their meaty matches,
and all of the studies, nine out of nine,
sometimes found comparable scores,
but mostly showed meat alternatives score better.
Based on their nutrient profiles,
plant-based meats and milks would be
expected to reduce chronic disease risk.
When it comes to heart
disease, stroke, and cancer,
plant-based meats would be
expected to decrease risk
of these killer diseases by about 3%
per daily serving replacement.
Now, whole soy foods might
take that down an extra 2%,
because they’re not weighed
down by the sodium issue,
but overall, swapping in even just one serving
of plant-based meat a day nationwide
could potentially prevent more than
100,000 cases of heart disease,
stroke, or cancer in the U.S. every year.
It’s hard to get everyone to go
all kale and quinoa overnight,
but a veggie burger should be easy.
100,000 cases prevented every year,
with a single daily serving
swap of plant-based meat.
Now, that’s just based on their
respective nutrient make-up—
like how much saturated fat
versus fiber they each had.
But remember how all the harmful effects
of ultra-processed foods are not necessarily
captured by their nutrient profile?
There are 16 proposed mechanisms
linking ultra-processed
foods to disease and death,
and balance of nutrients is only one of those 16.
And so, using these 16 criteria,
normally, when you compare
ultra-processed products
to the foods they were designed to replace,
for example, water vs. Kool-Aid,
or fruit vs. fruit-flavored candy,
the ultra-processed product tends to do worse
and not just because of the
junkier nutrient profile.
However, plant-based meats
appear to be the exception,
better in most ways compared to the
foods they were designed to replace.
We already covered nutrient profile,
where plant-based meat tended to
score healthier than regular meat,
based on every study,
using every major nutrient profiling system.
I don’t have time to go
through all of these right now.
For those who want dive a little deeper,
I had a paper published this year on the subject,
which you’re welcome to download.
This Thursday, the 21st,
I’m going to be giving a
three-hour webinar on the subject,
where I will go into detail through
all the rest of those criteria,
and I’ve got a book coming out on ultra-processed
that will be out in January;
so, you’ll have all the references handy,
but with limited time,
I’m going to skip through a bunch of these,
though happy to talk about them in Q&A.
In terms of additives,
I’ve been long concerned that Red
No. 3 hadn’t been banned from food,
given that it was banned over 30 years ago
from anything going on our
skin, due to cancer risk.
But it’s still ok to eat?
Thankfully, California passed a Food Safety Act,
set to ban Red Dye No. 3 by 2027.
So, in 2027, Loma Linda Big Franks
will be illegal to sell in Loma Linda
but would still be available to
potentially contribute to cancer risk
throughout the rest of the country.
But, the FDA finally decided to ban it from food,
35 years after it removed it from cosmetics,
starting in 2027 as well.
So, for now, this veggie bacon is
considered too toxic to rub on your skin
but okay to eat—
at least, for the next two years.
Why has the pork bacon industry
figured out how to use cherry powder
as a coloring before the
plant-based bacon industry?
The most harmful additive in
plant-based meat, is ironically,
really the most traditional and that’s salt,
contributing to the #1 dietary risk
factor for death on planet Earth,
excess sodium consumption.
It is one of the most common ingredients
in plant-based meat alternatives.
But, also one of the most frequent ingredients
used in conventional meat processing,
and not just in processed meat.
While the #1 source of sodium for
kids in this country is pizza,
and in older individuals bread,
one of the reasons the #1 source of sodium
for those aged 19 through 50 in this country
is chicken is because injecting
raw chicken with saltwater
is a widespread practice in the poultry industry,
something they’ve been doing since the 1970s,
resulting in raw chicken breasts reaching
as much as 400mg of sodium or more,
six times more than they’d naturally have.
When it comes to salt, how does
meat and plant-based meat compare?
A systematic review found that
the average levels of sodium
were not significantly different overall
between plant-based and conventional meat,
which is not great,
but there are some products are improving.
When I created a chart five years ago for UBS,
Beyond Meat burgers had 390 milligrams of sodium,
which is in the typical 290 to 400
range of a regular American hamburger,
but the current version is 20% lower at 310 mg,
thanks to the use of potassium salt,
potassium chloride instead of sodium chloride,
and Impossible now has a
beef “lite,” with only 260.
Ideally, we would be under 180,
meeting the World Health
Organization’s recommendation
for less than a 1:1 ratio of sodium to calories.
All the foods we eat ideally should
have less sodium than calories.
Plant-based meat tends to be better
when it comes to some additives,
like carcinogenic nitrite preservatives,
similar with salt and sugar,
and worse with emulsifiers,
which might be expected to
hurt the gut microbiome,
but vegetarians who eat plant-based meat
actually end up with lower rates
of irritable bowel syndrome
than those who don’t,
which suggests that at least on that metric
the emulsifiers don’t seem to be a problem.
In fact, all three studies on
the impact of plant-based meat
show microbiome benefits;
for example, this randomized, controlled trial
analyzing stool samples before and after
even just swapping out about
five meals of meat a week
for plant-based meat,
confirming that even just the
occasional replacement of meat
may promote positive changes
in the gut microbiome.
In the second trial, the Mycomeat study,
people were randomized to replace
a few servings of meat a day
with the mycoprotein meat Quorn—
made from the mushroom kingdom
rather than the plant kingdom.
This swap not only increases the abundance
of beneficial microbes in the gut,
it reduces fecal genotoxicity,
which is the amount of DNA damage that
their feces can cause colon cells.
Now, that may just have been because
they were cutting down on meat,
but on the Quorn, there was
a boost in good bacteria,
like lactobacillus, which may have benefits,
suggesting that the fiber in mycoprotein
may have prebiotic potential.
The two-week swap did not
seem to be long enough time
to affect TMAO levels, though,
but in the 8-week Stanford SWAP-MEAT study,
in which two or more servings
a day of beef, pork, or chicken
were swapped out with plant-based
beef, pork, or chicken,
several cardiovascular risk factors improved,
including TMAO, which stands
for trimethylamine n-oxide,
considered like the smoking gun in
gut microbiome-disease interactions.
When we eat meat, dairy, or eggs,
the carnitine and choline get turned by
certain bad gut bugs into trimethylamine,
which is oxidized by our liver into TMAO
which can go on to damage various
organ systems throughout the body.
So, the cardiovascular harm from eggs and meat
is more than just cholesterol and saturated fat.
TMAO is linked to some of our deadliest diseases—
cardiovascular disease, diabetes,
high blood pressure, stroke, cancer.
Check out those P values.
Those, are my kind of P values.
Like six times ten to the negative 21st.
That means you’d only get a
finding that extreme by chance
if you ran the study about
a billion trillion times.
So, TMAO may also mean time to
minimize intake of animal products,
which we can do by switching to plant products.
Plant-based meals can also be better
for the upper digestive tract.
If you randomize people to eat
chicken, cheese, fish, and steak,
versus tofu, soy steaks, seitan, and soy burgers,
you see twice as much heartburn
after the animal protein meal
than after the plant-protein meal.
And stick a probe down their throats,
and after the animal products,
you see three times as much acid
exposure refluxing up from their stomach
into their esophagus.
The bottom line is that,
unlike almost any other ultra-processed product,
plant-based meat appears to be the rare case
in which ultra-processed products
are actually better, overall,
than the foods they were designed to replace.
Now, this probably says less how healthy they are
and more about how really
unhealthy modern meat is.
Take food safety, for example.
In response to a Super Bowl ad
placed by a meat-industry-funded lobbying group
questioning plant-based meat for
its hard-to-spell ingredients,
Impossible Foods responded with a parody,
questioning an unintentional
additive in conventional meat.
Fecal contamination of the
carcass in the slaughter plant
is considered unavoidable,
and though there are methods for removing
visible fecal contamination on meat,
and even experimental imaging technologies
designed to detect more
“diluted fecal contaminations,”
we’re still left at a retail level
with guess what proportion of meat
contaminated with fecal
bacteria at the grocery store?
About 85% of ground beef and turkey
contaminated with fecal bacteria,
and about half of chicken on store
shelves, and a third of pork,
found contaminated with Enterococci,
which is used as a marker of
fecal contamination of food.
But you don’t have to cook the
crap out of plant-based meat,
because there shouldn’t be any crap to begin with.
Fecal contamination is not just unseemly
but a critical public health issue.
Fecal matter is considered the main source
of some of our most serious foodborne pathogens
like Salmonella and Campylobacter.
Salmonella is the leading cause of foodborne
hospitalizations in the United States
and the #1 cause of foodborne death,
and 1 in 4 packages of chicken sampled
in the United States by the USDA
contaminated with Salmonella,
1 in 8 packages of ground turkey,
1 in 24 packages of pork,
and 1 in 67 packages of ground beef,
and 1 in 4 packages of retail chicken.
Campylobacter, which sickens more
than 800,000 Americans a year,
is also found in every 1 in 3 or
1 in 4 packages of retail chicken.
Even just shopping for meat can be risky,
as disease-causing fecal bacteria can
contaminate the outer packaging of meat.
But, the good news is that food-borne
illnesses are largely preventable,
and the simplest approach
to reduce their occurrence
is to greatly reduce the consumption
of animal products like meat.
They’re intestinal bugs,
and since plants don’t have any intestines,
we can reduce the risk with plant-based meat,
though there are always cases of
manure run-off contaminating crops.
But the leading causes of large food-borne
outbreaks of food poisoning are all meat,
and every single one of the
top pathogen-food combinations
that cause the greatest burden of
disease are all animal products,
mostly meat.
That second one is toxoplasma,
which is a brain parasite that may
infect a million Americans a year,
making it a leading source of severe
foodborne illness in the United States.
What may end up in your brain
may start in your burger.
Tapeworms in your brain from pork
have become an increasingly important
emerging infection in the United States.
What you think is a migraine
may not be a migraine.
This is what they found in the brain
of our current Secretary of
Health and Human Services.
You may even get bladder
infections from eating meat,
particularly poultry, urinary tract infections,
or viral hepatitis from pork
products—hepatitis E infection.
There aren’t any prions in plants either,
the cause of fatal spongiform brain diseases,
which is why there’s a mad cow disease,
but not a mad Quorn disease.
And I didn’t include other meat-borne pathogens,
like trichinosis or E. coli O157:H7,
which still sickens 50,000
Americans a year, mostly from beef,
or the 100,000 sickened by
yersinia-infected pork every year,
but let’s just stick to the major pathogens,
some of which can become antibiotic-resistant.
Consuming contaminated meat with
antibiotic-resistant bacteria
is considered a severe public health hazard.
To help compensate for the overcrowded,
stressful, unhygienic conditions,
animals raised for food are
dosed en masse with antibiotics.
Lots of antibiotics. This is in kilos;
so, we’re talking 10 million pounds a
year of medically-important antibiotics.
So, we give farm animals in the United States
more than a million pounds
of penicillin drugs a year.
Four thousand tons of tetracyclines.
Millions of pounds of drugs, laced
right into their food and water.
Antibiotics important to human medicine
being fed to cows, pigs, chickens by the ton—
by the thousands of tons every year.
And so now in chicken breasts, for example,
most of the Salmonella and
Campylobacter found is now resistant
to at least one class of antibiotics,
and about half of the Salmonella is resistant
to three or more classes of drugs.
Even organic meat raised without antibiotics
can be contaminated with
multidrug-resistant bacteria,
often because there is cross-contamination
in the slaughter plant.
It’s funny—in the cover story of Consumer Reports
that urged retailers to stop selling
meat produced with antibiotics,
they noted, some store employee confusion:
“An assistant manager at one store,
when asked by a shopper for
meats raised without antibiotics,
responded, ‘Wait, you mean,
like, veggie burgers?'” Exactly.
Antibiotic-resistance genes can
also be transmitted through meat,
which can then transfer to
other pathogens in our gut,
as well as residues of the
antibiotic drugs themselves,
which is itself considered a
serious public health threat.
You can correlate how much meat people eat;
you can just measure the amount of antibiotics
flowing out of their urine every day.
These drug residues in the
meat can cause allergies,
nerve damage, liver damage,
reproductive disorders,
bone marrow toxicity, even increased cancer risk,
not to mention what eating antibiotics
every day is doing to your gut microbiome.
In contrast, the production of
plant-based meat involves no guts,
no feces, no antibiotics necessary.
In addition to antibiotics, livestock
may be fed or injected with hormones.
Currently, seven hormone
drugs are approved by the FDA
to bulk up the production of milk and meat.
In Europe, there exists a
total ban on all such use.
But even without injected hormones,
animal products naturally contain hormones
because they come from animals.
I already touched on processing contaminants,
but there are also industrial contaminants
that build up in the food chain,
like certain pesticides, PCBs, heavy metals,
and ﬂame retardant chemicals that
end up concentrating in meat.
Can’t you just choose organic meat?
Surprisingly, the consumption of organic meat
does not seem to diminish
the carcinogenic potential
associated with these industrial pollutants.
If you look at the micropollutants
and chemical residues
in conventional vs. organic meat,
several environmental contaminants—like
dioxins, PCBs, lead, arsenic
sometimes measured at signiﬁcantly
higher levels in organic meat,
though cooking does draw off some of the fat
where the PCBs are concentrated.
Seafood seems to be the exception, though,
with steaming, for example,
generally increasing the concentration
of contaminants like mercury.
There is, however, no mercury
added to plant-based tuna.
When researchers tested retail meat
for the presence of 33 chemicals with
calculated carcinogenic potential,
like organochlorine pesticides
like DDT and dioxin-like PCBs,
they concluded in order to
reduce our risk of cancer,
we should limit our ingestion
of beef, pork, or chicken
to a maximum of five servings—a month.
Meat presents the only scenario
in which ultra-processed products
were designed to replace foods
that we know cause cancer,
in fact, the #1 cancer killer of
nonsmokers, colorectal cancer.
These are foods in desperate need of replacement.
Processed meat—bacon, ham,
hot dogs, lunch meat, sausage—
is considered a known human carcinogen,
leading major cancer centers, like Mount Sinai,
Memorial Sloan Kettering, and MD Anderson,
to recommend flat-out avoid processed meat.
All in all, plant-based meat is
better than animal-based meat
in about 40 different ways.
Now obviously, some of these categories
are more important than others.
The fact that bacon is officially
designated as cancer-causing
is more important than the fact
that it may have a few more calories
than plant-based bacon.
But cancer is just killer #2.
The leading cause of death in
men and women is heart disease,
and hidden in that nutrient profile,
are the three things that raise LDL cholesterol:
saturated fat, trans fat, and dietary cholesterol.
Yes, there are other factors,
like TMAO and sodium.
But LDL cholesterol, also
known as bad cholesterol,
is unequivocally recognized
as the principal driver
in the development of atherosclerotic
cardiovascular disease,
our leading cause of death.
Basically, we should try to
get our LDL as low as possible.
When it comes to LDL lowering for
the prevention of heart disease,
“Lower for longer is better.”
Even if your LDL is quote-unquote normal;
even if other heart disease risk
factors are considered optimal,
still, of utmost importance to control it.
So, if LDL is the primary
driver of our primary killer,
if you could just know one thing about a food,
if could just ask one question,
it would be “What does this
food do to my LDL cholesterol?”
So, we’re looking at nutrition labels for
saturated fat, trans fat, and cholesterol,
since any intake above zero increases
LDL cholesterol and, therefore,
increases our risk of coronary heart disease.
In terms of saturated fat and cholesterol,
animal meats are the main
source in the American diet,
and with the removal of partially
hydrogenated oils from the U.S. food supply,
such that these other sources are now banned,
animal products are now the
leading source of trans fat as well
(since meat and dairy
naturally contain trans fat).
Online, some bloggers parrot
egg industry propaganda
that the 2015 U.S. Dietary Guidelines
removed its dietary cholesterol limit,
whereas if anyone actually
bothered to read the guidelines,
they’d see that the guidelines actually
strengthened their recommendation,
telling Americans to “eat as little
dietary cholesterol as possible,”
as recommended by the Institute of Medicine,
the most prestigious medical
body in the United States.
This advice was reiterated in the
subsequent dietary guidelines:
“The National Academies recommends
that dietary cholesterol consumption
to be as low as possible.”
While eggs are the most concentrated
source of cholesterol gram-for-gram,
the greatest cholesterol contribution
in the overall American diet is meat,
including poultry and fish.
Since cholesterol is present
only in animal-derived foods,
it’s not surprising that plant-based
meat contains little or no cholesterol
(unless they have cheese
or something added in it).
And saturated fat content is
usually low in plant-based meat
compared to regular meat, averaging
to one half and one third.
You can see that illustrated graphically here,
where the conventional meat is
those orange bars across the top,
so better across the board,
often by a large margin.
This is as true in Europe as well
as in South Africa and the U.S.—
where plant-based meat may only
average a third of the saturated fat.
Swapping out meat for plant-based meat
significantly lowers saturated fat,
but does this translate into lower LDL?
That’s really what we care about.
Well, you don’t really know,
until you put it to the test.
Here’s a meta-analysis of 10
randomized controlled trials
replacing some or all meat with
plant-based or mycoprotein-based meats,
and within an average of six weeks,
saw a 15-point drop in LDL cholesterol.
What does that mean in terms of disease risk?
Maintaining a 15-point drop in LDL for five years
would be expected to decrease your
risk of heart disease by about 10%,
and after a dozen years by more like 15%,
and across a lifetime by more like 25%.
And risk reduction is independent of baseline LDL,
meaning you get about the
same relative risk reduction,
even if your LDL is so-called
normal, less than 100.
One would also expect the use of egg
substitutes to reduce cardiovascular risk,
given that eggs are the most concentrated
source of dietary cholesterol.
What about substituting soymilk for cow’s milk?
Based on 17 randomized, controlled trials,
drinking soymilk instead of cow’s milk
resulted in significant
improvements in blood pressure,
in cholesterol, in inflammation,
an 8-point drop in systolic blood pressure,
a 5-point drop in diastolic blood pressure,
a 7-point drop in LDL
cholesterol switching to soy,
as well as a drop in c‑reactive protein,
so less inflammation as well.
Over a lifetime,
that 7-point drop in LDL could drop our
risk of heart disease by more than 10%,
just making a single dietary swap from cow to soy.
Now, the benefit only accrues
if your cholesterol stays down.
And it turns out, it may even get better.
In a four-year study in which
diabetics were randomized
to swap out half their animal protein
for ultra-processed plant protein,
their LDL went down year after year,
ending up 26 points lower than the control group.
Whoa, that could net you a nearly
40% drop in risk, over a lifetime,
of our #1 killer, just swapping out
half of their animal protein servings.
An estimated 20 million
Americans have heart disease,
having about 800,000 heart attacks a year.
If we started swapping our animal
products for plant products,
imagine how many lives could be saved
by even a 10% drop in heart disease.
Instead of swapping out a
burger for a veggie burger,
why not just switch to chicken and fish?
Because, it doesn’t work.
A meta-analysis of randomized, controlled trials
that compared the cholesterol effects
of beef versus poultry-and/or-ﬁsh
found no significant difference in terms of LDL.
And an updated meta-analysis
of four times as many studies
also found no benefit to
switching to chicken and poultry,
and the beef was actually
found to be better than fish,
which they attribute to using particularly
lean cuts of beef as the comparator,
particularly because the beef industry
is the one that funded these studies.
But even organic, grass-fed beef appeared
to be no match for plant-based meat,
as shown in the Stanford SWAP-MEAT trial.
With processed meat officially
classified as a known human carcinogen,
global health organizations flat-out
recommend avoid processed meat,
but looking at six health outcomes—
colorectal cancer, breast cancer,
ischemic heart disease, type 2 diabetes,
and two types of stroke—
the optimal amount of unprocessed
red meat may be zero as well,
but even a 30% reduction in both types of meat
could lead to a million fewer
cases of type 2 diabetes,
hundreds of thousands of fewer
cases of cardiovascular disease,
and tens of thousands fewer cases of
cancer and premature death over a decade.
Diets high in processed and red meat
are also the two single leading causes of
diet-related disability in the United States,
responsible for more than a million
years lived in disability annually—
three times more than diets high in
sugar-sweetened beverages, for example,
and more than two million
years of healthy life lost,
based on the most comprehensive
analysis of risk factors
for death and disability in history.
Millions of years of lost
life every year in the U.S.
because people are eating diets
high in red and processed meat.
What do they define as high, though?
A diet “high” in processed meat is
defined as any intake of processed meat.
And a diet high in red meat?
High as in any intake of red meat.
So, millions of years of life
lost in the United States,
because people are eating more
than zero red and processed meat.
Higher intake of meat in general—
red meat, white meat, processed, unprocessed—
also associated with an increased risk
of death from all-causes put together.
If people swapped out 75% of their meat,
up to 50,000 lives a year could
be saved in high income countries.
What would happen if the
whole world cut out all meat?
We would save an estimated 7 million lives a year,
and if humanity cut out all animal products,
we might annually save 8 million lives.
Hanging in the balance!
The bottom line is that veggie
burgers are not Twinkies,
even though they’re both classified
as ultra-processed foods.
Now, there are two directions
we can go with that fact.
We can decry the very concept
of ultra-processed foods.
Or we can take what I would
argue is a better tact:
keep the baby; throw out the bathwater.
In other words, not deny
ultra-processed foods tend to be worse,
not deny that plant-based
meats are ultra-processed,
but rather that despite this classification,
plant-based meats and milks are the rare exception
in that they compare well with the
foods they were designed to replace,
in some cases, potentially
even saving thousands of lives.
But there is some merit to the argument
that the ultra-processed concept is
not as useful as many people think.
If you look at the three big Harvard cohorts—
200,000 people followed for decades.
Yes, total ultra-processed foods intake
was associated with cardiovascular risk,
but if you break it down,
the risk is driven exclusively by soda and meat.
Sugar-sweetened beverages,
a little from artificially sweetened beverages,
and the rest from processed meat, poultry, fish.
If you exclude soda and meat,
the relationship between ultra-processed
food and cardiovascular disease
disappears completely.
So, nutritional advice for cardiovascular health
should consider the differential consequences
of group-speciﬁc ultra-processed foods,
and speciﬁcally, that means
processed meats and soft drinks
should be discouraged.
What about mortality?
Yes, those who ate the most
ultra-processed foods in general
had a higher risk of dying prematurely,
but it mattered what kind
of ultra-processed foods,
with ready-to-eat meat,
poultry, and seafood products
showing particularly strong
associations with mortality.
The apparent worst ultra-processed food
when it comes to dying prematurely in general?
Meat/poultry/seafood.
The worst when it comes to dying from cancer?
The worst when it comes to dying
from cardiovascular disease?
Meat/poultry/seafood.
The worst when it comes to dying
from lung diseases like emphysema?
Meat/poultry/seafood.
The worst when it comes to dying
from neurodegenerative diseases?
(Ice cream).
And the worst when it comes
to dying from other causes?
Meat/poultry/seafood.
Bottom line,
the major factors contributing
to the harmful effects
of ultra-processed foods on mortality are
processed meat, poultry, fish, and soda.
So, the negative, life-shortening
effects of ultra-processed food
is really mostly talking about the
negative, life-shortening effect
of ultra-processed meat like burgers,
chicken nuggets, and fish sticks.
Ideally, we would have a study that
specifically looked at meat alternatives.
And, here we go: a quarter-million
people followed for over a decade,
and while the higher consumption
of ultra-processed foods in general
increases the risk of cancer and
cardiovascular disease and diabetes,
but that was driven by ultra-processed
animal products and soda,
not plant-based meats.
They specifically studied plant-based
alternatives and found no increased risk.
And when it comes to diabetes,
plant-based meat and milk appears to cut
the risk of developing diabetes in half.
Animal-based products were associated
with more than twice the risk;
plant-based alternatives with less than half.
So, when the authors conclude
that higher consumption
of ultra-processed foods may increase
the risk of cancer and other diseases,
their data really only show
that the consumption of foods
of animal origin and soft drinks
is associated with such a risk,
and indeed, when the authors were challenged
to go back and exclude animal foods and beverages,
the relationship between ultra-processed
foods and multiple diseases disappears.
That’s also what a systematic review and
meta-analysis of all such studies showed.
The only categories of ultra-processed
foods associated with higher mortality
were sweetened beverages and meat.
So, wait.
If the only ultra-processed food that
appears to be killing people is meat,
then in that case, instead of
being a part of the problem,
plant-based meats may be the solution
to the ultra-processed problem.
Let me say that again;
instead of being a part of the problem,
plant-based meats may be the solution
to the ultra-processed problem.
The one other ultra-processed study
that separated out plant-based meats
looked at telomere length, which
is used to measure cellular aging.
Their study found that a higher
consumption of total ultra-processed foods
was associated with a shorter telomere length,
a sign of accelerated aging.
However, some subclasses of ultra-processed foods
were associated with longer telomere length,
suggesting slower aging.
And, the class of foods associated
with the longest telomeres?
Vegetarian alternatives: plant-based meat.
The most important question
in all of nutrition may be,
“Compared with what?”
The effects of any given food depend on
what that food is being compared against.
So, is plant-based meat healthy?
Compared to the animal products
they were intended to replace?
Absolutely.
Plant-based meat alternatives are more
healthful than the meat they replace,
but perhaps less so than whole plant foods,
such as legumes and whole grains.
Wait, just perhaps less so?
This is how ultra-processed
plant meat compares to meat.
This, is how unprocessed plants compare to meat.
Not only making up for all the shortfalls,
but if we add an even better category,
whole plant foods do even
better, in many categories.
For example, bean-based meat averages
five times less saturated fat
than their meat comparators,
but actual beans have 40 times less:
half the trans fat or no trans fat.
Five grams of fiber is certainly better than zero,
but nine grams is even better.
And there are interventional trials
demonstrating the greater benefits.
For example, better at fighting
insulin resistance and inflammation.
So certainly, whole foods for the win,
but plant-based meat alternatives,
they are not designed to
replace whole plant foods,
instead to offer a steppingstone
in the transition away from meat.
I think of it like meat methadone.
Or, as Professor Gardner put it,
“I’m hoping that plant-based meats
will be the gateway drug to legumes.”
This is how the transition to
healthier diets is envisioned,
from the global burden of disease,
to the global relief of disease,
as people use plant-based
and mycoprotein-based meats
to transition toward a more
whole food, plant-based diet.
With the added saturated fat and sodium,
plant-based meats are not
healthy—but, they are healthier.
They are healthier than the foods
they were designed to replace.
They are better, but not the best.
Yes, nutrition policies and dietary guidelines,
the bottom line is that we should
continue to emphasize a diet
rich in whole plant foods.
Indeed, if all meat in high income
countries were replaced with whole legumes,
we could potentially decrease
overall mortality rates by 5 or 6%.
That means saving 180,000 lives
in the United States every year.
If instead, we replaced meat with
processed or ultra-processed plants,
we’d only save about 130,000 Americans a year
(about a 4% drop in overall mortality).
That’s still over 100,000 people saved every year.
So, we shouldn’t let the perfect
be the enemy of the good.
Plant-based meat alternatives
are better than the alternative.
Or as one study put it,
plant-based meat can be
considered “meat with benefits.”
Thank you so much.
Wow, what a way to end the conference.
That was absolutely phenomenal.
I think he deserves another round of applause.
All right, Dr. Greger, do you
have time for two questions?
Let's do it.
All right.
So, on one of the slides that you just ended on,
there was, right at the bottom,
it spoke about mold toxins being
higher in plant-based meats.
Could you comment on that?
Yeah. So there's mycotoxins.
So, I have a bunch of videos on mycotoxins
that affect the majority of the
food crops grown in the world today.
And although, you know,
animals that eat contaminated moldy food crops
can build up these mycotoxins like aflatoxin,
the plant products tend to
have higher levels in general.
And so the concern is—
so there was a modeling study in Europe
that suggested that if everybody switched
from their current meat consumption
to 100% plant-based meat,
the mycotoxin exposure, the increased
mycotoxin exposure that they get,
based on, you know, studies of
hundreds of plant-based products,
would cause, between one in one million
or one in two million more cases
of liver cancer because of the aflatoxin content.
So, one in one or two million
people would get liver cancer
that wouldn’t have gotten liver cancer
if they had stuck with the meat.
Of course, the amount of colorectal
cancer that would be prevented
by switching to plant-based
meat would far overwhelm that,
you know, one million cases
or one in two million cases.
Having said that, it's
still not acceptable, right?
I mean, so these plant-based companies—
so I encourage—so in the book I talk
about how really they should be tested.
You can certainly—
I mean, you can test for, you know, your feed,
the, you know, the soy or whatever
you're using in your products,
and you just make sure that
they don't reach levels
that could cause any harm, right?
We don't just want overwhelming benefit over harm.
How about overwhelming benefit with no harm?
And so, unfortunately, mycotoxins is one
of the things that is actually lower—
the concern is lower in meat—
but still overwhelming for trying
to prevent cancer overwhelmingly.
But that doesn't put plant-based
meat companies off the hook,
and I encourage them to start testing to make sure
that they indeed drop their levels lower.
And a question that actually stumped
Dr. Christopher Gardner earlier.
Bring it.
You have to answer in one word.
One word?
What is your favorite
plant-based ultra-processed food
after all this research that you've done?
He couldn't answer?
It took him a while.
Ah, what did he finally say?
Well, no, no, no. Don't, don't.
Well, okay, this is actually controversial
whether it's actually considered ultra-processed,
but, so tempeh, some regard that
as an ultra-processed product
because some—you can't really
make it in your home kitchen
because they use these, you know, fancy processes.
You actually can make tempeh,
but it's quite a process.
And if you read the
instructions for making tempeh,
it's like if there's black mold, that's fine.
But if it's gray mold, then
you don't want, you know,
it's like, I'll let you make it.
But that's an example of a processed product
that's actually healthier than the whole food.
So, the whole food is soybeans,
and then they process it
by adding these, you know,
these micro-protein threads,
you know, this culture,
and they ferment it into tempeh.
So, it actually ends—
it's the rare, it's a rare processed
product essentially healthier
than just the regular whole food.
It has more spermidine, more
ergothioneine, all sorts of things.
So, I love that as like, you know, there's
a processed product I can get behind.
You're actually processing
it to make it healthier,
and that's unfortunately all too rare.
Dr. Gardner said soy milk.
Oh, not sure which one.
So, it was better.
Are we allowed to know the title
of your new book that's coming out?
Yes, so, I've got three
books coming out this year.
Three books next year.
So, October 10th is the cholesterol-lowering book
and then in January it will
be the ultra-processed book.
It's got some boring title like
Ultra-Processed Foods: Controversies,
Concerns, and Exceptions,
something like that.
But anyway, it basically
goes through all the criteria
and just has all the references so
you can use this as a reference book,
and then, yeah,
and this Thursday I'll be
doing a three-hour webinar.
So, basically, I’ll be giving a
three-hour version of this presentation.
If you thought this presentation was too long,
imagine adding two hours to this presentation.
I mean, so I go, you know,
I skipped through all those.
It's like, okay, well, let's not skip through it.
So, I talk about the mycotoxins.
I talk about everything.
So, if you really want to, like,
do the deep dive this Thursday,
you can watch the extended version.
All right, that's all we have time for.
Thank you so much.
Another round of applause.